Finding Aid for the Charles F. Delzell Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Charles F. Delzell Papers
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0105
41.67 linear_feet
- Correspondence
  - A – America-Italy Society (Box 1)
  - American Political Science Association – Casada, James A. (Box 2)
  - Carrafiello, Susan Benton – Da Capo Press (Box 3)
  - Dade, William C. – Fausz, Daniel (Box 4)
  - Fehl, Noah – Hall, Hines (Box 5)
  - Hall, Kermit – Holt, Rinehart, and Winston (Box 6)
  - Holtman, Robert – Journal of Military History (Box 7)
  - Journal of Modern History – Macmillan Publishers (Box 8)
  - Maddux, Robert – National Archives Conference on Documentation (Box 9)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) – Painter, Borden (Box 10)
  - Pang, Eul-Soo – Princeton University Press-Mussolini’s Enemies, etc. (Box 11)
  - Progressive Magazine – Salomone, William A. (Box 12)
  - Salvadori, Prof. Max – Sloan, Lin (Box 13)
  - Smalling, Nancy – Society for Italian Historical Studies (SIHS) (Box 14)
  - Southern Historical Association (SHA) – Stanford University Press (Box 15)
  - State College of New York-Geneseo – Valsechhi, Prof. Franco (Box 16)
  - Vanderbilt-in-France – Yale University Press (Box 17)
  - Yazdi, Ahmad Todd – Ziemke, Prof. Earl (Box 18)
- Writings/Conferences
  - Correspondence and reports for NEH Summer Seminars for College Teachers, 1996 and at Vanderbilt University, 1996, on “Europe in the Age of Fascism, 1919-1945: A Historical Re-Examination.” Directed by Charles F. Delzell.
  - Reports and papers presented in 1960 in Stockholm at the 14th International Congress of Historical Sciences (ICHS), and in 1975 in San Francisco at the 17th International Congress of Historical Sciences (ICHS). Delzell attended both and was a member of the U.S. Planning Committee for the 1975 conference. (Box 19)
  - American Committee on the History of the Second World War (later re-named the World War II Studies Association), c. 1968-1974 (Box 20)
  - Correspondence and activities, 1968-1985 (Box 20)
  - Paper on “American Aid to Resistance Movements” presented in Stuttgart, Summer 1985, at the International Congress of Historical Sciences (ICHS). (Box 20)
  - American Committee on the History of the Second World War (later re-named the World War II Studies Association) Newsletters, 1985-1997 (Box 21)
  - Research documents from the national Archives for Delzell’s paper, “American Aid to Resistance Movements in World War II,” presented in Stuttgart, Summer 1985, at the International Congress of Historical Sciences (ICHS). (Box 21)
  - Correspondence and articles pertaining to Italy, written for “Encyclopedia Americana” and the “Americana Annuals” covering the years from 1960 to 1998. (Grolier, Inc. now publishes the encyclopedia) (Box 22)
  - Files pertaining to various conferences in which Delzell participated: conference in Leuven, Belgium, September 6, 1990, on the History of European Ideas: “European Nationalism: Toward 1992” (in which Delzell presented a paper on Altiero Spinelli and the European Federalist Movement in Italy). (Box 23)
  - Also a conference at the Woodrow Wilson Center, Washington, on Italy, etc. (Box 23)
  - Notes and early drafts on an uncompleted manuscript on “Fascism: Conflicting Interpretations.” (Box 24)
- Personal records
  - Curriculum Vitae and Publications List (Box 25)
  - Appointment to Vanderbilt, 1952 (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous Vanderbilt correspondence, 1952 and following (Box 25)
  - Applications for various research grants (Box 25)
  - Promotions (Box 25)
  - Chair of History Department, 1970-1973, June-December 1983, September-December 1986 (Box 25)
  - Senior Research Associate (Box 25)
  - VIPPS, 1981-1986 (Box 25)
  - European Studies Program (Box 25)
  - Retirement Talk 1989 and letters of congratulation (Box 25)
  - Grade records of courses taught since, 1952 (Box 25)
- Friends of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library
  - Various files covering the 1980s and 1990s while Delzell was serving as a member of the Board of Directors and/or President of the Friends. (Box 26)
- Lecture Notes
  - Class lecture notes for Vanderbilt courses taught by Delzell on “Europe, 1900-1980s” (HIST 225 A/B, 226 A/B) (Box 28)
  - Class lecture notes for Vanderbilt courses taught by Delzell on “Europe, 1900-1980s” (HIST 225 A/B, 226 A/B). (Box 28)
  - Class lecture notes for Modern Italian History course (HIST 232 A/B), covering period from 1700-1980s (Box 28)
  - Various additional lectures pertaining to Italy (Box 28)
- Theses/Dissertations
  - Personal (extra) copies of dissertations and theses in history directed by Delzell: Nigro, Louis J. Propaganda, Politics, and the New Diplomacy: The Impact of Wilsonian Propaganda on Politics and Public Opinion in Italy, 1917-1919. Ph.D. dissertation, 1979 (Box 29)
  - Linsenmeyer, William S. Allied Relations with Italy, 1943-1944. Ph.D. dissertation, 1972 (Box 29)
  - Schrader, Phyllis Kent Greenwood. Jules Romains’s Les Hommes de Bonne Volonté: The Novelist Deals with History. Ph.D. dissertation, 1974 (Box 29)
  - Lavine, Marcia Fishel. Count Ciano: Foreign Affairs and Policy Determination in Fascist Italy, January 1939-June 1940. Ph.D. dissertation, 1977 (Box 29)
  - Carrafiello, Susan Benton. "The Tombs of the Living": Prisons and Prison Reform in Italy, 1861-1915. Ph.D. dissertation, 1992 (Box 29)
- Correspondence
  - Thrupp, Sylvia L. (Box 30)
  - Spitz, Lewis W. (Box 30)
  - Stone, Lawrence (Box 30)
  - Thernstrom, Stephan (Box 30)
  - Woodward, C. Vann (Box 30)
  - Wright, Gordon (Box 30)
  - Mazlish, Bruce (Box 30)
  - Borah, Woodrow (Box 30)
  - Cohen, I. Bernard (Box 30)
  - Hall, John W. (Box 30)
  - Leopold, Richard W. (Box 30)
  - Lockridge, Kenneth A. (Box 30)
  - Hobbs, Provost Nicholas – Symposium Correspondence, “The Future of History” (Box 30)
  - Wilcoxin, Reba – re: The Future of History, 1976 (Box 30)
- Conferences/Academic Career
  - Future of History Symposium (Box 30)
  - Faculty Senate (Box 30)
  - College of Arts & Science (Box 30)
  - Conference at Florence of American Historical Association & Societa Degli Storici Italiani, October 25-27, 1983 (Box 30)
  - American Historical Association, 1974-1977 (Box 30)
  - Vanderbilt Centennial Fellows Project, 1974/1975 (Box 30)
  - American Historical Association Organizing Committee of the XIV International Congress of Historical Sciences, San Francisco, 1975 (Treadgold, Chairman) (Box 30)
  - American Historical Association Council, 1974-1977 (Box 31)
  - Council Agenda, December 27, 1974 (Box 31)
  - American Historical Association Ad Hoc Committee on International Historical Activities (1974/1975), Charles F. Delzell, Chairman (Box 31)
  - Council Agenda, September 28, 1975 (Box 31)
  - Unlabeled: materials on Council Meeting, September 8, 1975 (Box 31)
  - Council Agenda, December 27, 1975 (Box 31)
  - Council Agenda, May 14-15, 1976 (Box 31)
  - American Historical Association Council – Executive Committee (1975) (Box 31)
  - American Historical Association Council – Executive Committee (1976) (Box 31)
  - Council Agenda, April 25-26, 1975 (Box 31)
  - Jacob Price, Chairman, American Historical Association Program Committee for 1976 – Correspondence involving Professional Division (Box 31)
  - Council Agenda, December 27, 1976 (Box 31)
  - American Historical Association – Work of Professional Division, 1976, Vice-President Jean Joughlin (Box 31)
  - Conference at Florence of American Historical Association & Societa Degli Storici Italiani, October 1983 (Box 32)
  - American Historical Association, 1974-1977 (Box 32)
  - Council Agenda, September 27-29, 1974 (Box 32)
  - “Report from the Beria Reserve” by Valentyn Moroz, 1974 (Box 32)
  - “Acta Persecutionis, A Document from Czechoslovakia,” 1975 (no author: directory of historians in German and English) (Box 32)
  - Loose press releases and memorandums (Box 32)
  - “Prepared by Moroz Defense Committee,” Human Rights Research, Inc., 1976 (Box 32)
  - Council, American Historical Association, December 1973-1976 through Meeting of, March 29-31, 1974 (Box 32)
  - Unlabeled: contains papers pertaining to “The Bi-National Conference of American and Italian Historians, University of Florence, Italy, October 1983” and “Comments by Charles F. Delzell of Vanderbilt University on the paper by professor Gaetano Cingari on ‘Social and Regional Imbalances in Italy’ “ (Box 32)
  - American Historical Association, December 28, 1976, 2:30-4:30, “Is There a Publishing Crisis? Historical Scholarship and Its Dissemination” (Box 32)
  - Future of History Symposium (Box 33)
  - Senate Committee on Academic Policies, 1984/1985 (Box 33)
  - Faculty Senate Papers, 1984/1985 (Box 33)
  - Vanderbilt University Press Committee, 1974 and following (Box 33)
  - Central Library Advisory Committee, 1981-1983 (Box 33)
  - Dean Ernest Q. Campbell, Graduate School, 1979 and following (Box 33)
  - Extra Copies – Senate Minutes by Delzell, 1965-1966 (Box 33)
  - College of Arts & Science (1979) – Rules and Procedures for Appointments, Renewals, Promotion, and Tenure in Arts and Science College (Box 33)
  - Graduate Faculty Delegate Assembly, 1979-1980, 1982-1983 (Box 33)
  - Music Advisory Committee, College of Arts and Science, 1986/1987 – 1988/1989 (Don Sherburne, Chair) (Box 33)
  - Musicology Search Committee, Douglas Lee, Chair, 1987/1988 (Box 33)
  - Faculty of Arts & Science, Agenda, January 1983 (Box 33)
  - Chancellor’s Search Committee for President of the University, 1977 (Box 33)
  - A.A.U.P., 1984/1985 (Box 33)
  - Committee on Vanderbilt-in-England, 1983/1984 (Box 33)
  - “Cornerstone” publication, College of Arts and Science, 1983 (Box 33)
  - Committee for Inauguration of Chancellor Wyatt (Box 33)
  - Blumstein’s University Committee on Tenure Policies, 1983/1984 (Box 33)
  - V.U. Press Committee, 1983 (Box 33)
  - Alexander Heard Distinguished Service Professor (Box 33)
  - Annual Report, College of Arts & Science, 1981/1982 (Box 33)
  - Faculty Senate, 1982 – Committee on Academic Policies & Services (Chairman: Jean Leblon) (Box 33)
  - Faculty Senate Papers, 1982/1983 (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous memorandums (Box 33)
  - Office Records (Box 33)
  - Interdepartmental Mail Envelope – material on College Program in Liberal Education (Box 33)
  - “Revised Report on the Ad Hoc University Committee on Appointments, Renewal and Tenure,”, March 20, 1985 (Box 33)
  - “The Future of History” – manuscript draft (Box 34)
  - “Storia della Storiografia Italiana,” 1944-1947 (periodical, 6 issues) (Box 35)
  - European Federalist Movement, Altiero Spinelli (c. 1950s-1960s) (Box 33)
  - Correspondence, Princeton University Press, c. 1950s and 1960s (Box 33)